<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The nevv distemper. Written by the author of the Loyall convert. Hilar. de Trin.Lib. 4. Hoc habet proprium Ecclesia; dum persecutionĕpatitur, floret; dum opprimitur, proficit; dum læditur, vincit: dum arguitur, intelligit; tunc stat quum superari videtur.</title>
            <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Q110</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E17_20</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99858900</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99858900</idno>
            <idno type="VID">110960</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91570)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 110960)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 3:E17[20])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The nevv distemper. Written by the author of the Loyall convert. Hilar. de Trin.Lib. 4. Hoc habet proprium Ecclesia; dum persecutionĕpatitur, floret; dum opprimitur, proficit; dum læditur, vincit: dum arguitur, intelligit; tunc stat quum superari videtur.</title>
                  <author>Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26, p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonard Lichfield, printer to the Vniversity,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Francis Quarles is the author of the Loyall convert. Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Noumb. 20th 1644".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:110960:1"/>
            <head>Die Martis 22. October. 1644.</head>
            <p>IT is this day Ordered by the Commons
Aſſembled in Parliament, That Maſter
<hi>Aſhurſt,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Gourdon,</hi> doe from this
Houſe give thankes to Mr. <hi>Vines,</hi> for the
great paines hee tooke in the Sermon hee
preached this day at the intreaty of the
Commons at St. <hi>Margarets, Weſtminſter,</hi> it
being a day eſpecially ſet apart for a publike
Humiliation, and to deſire him to print
his Sermon. And it is Ordered that none
ſhall preſume to print his Sermon without
being authorized under the hand writing of
the ſaid Maſter <hi>Vines.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>I appo<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Abel Roper</hi> to print this Sermon.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Richard Vines.</signed>
               </closer>
            </postscript>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:110960:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE NEVV
DISTEMPER.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN
By the AUTHOR of the
Loyall Convert.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hilar. de Trin. Lib. 4.</bibl>
               <p>Hoc habet proprium Eccleſia; dum perſecutione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> patitur, floret;
dum opprimitur, proficit; dum laeditur, vincit; dum arguitur,
intelligit; tunc ſtat quum ſuperari videtur.</p>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD,
Printed by LEONARD LICHFIELD,
Printer to the Vniverſity. 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:110960:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:110960:2"/>
            <head>THE NEW
DISTEMPER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is in a Principality, or in a Republique,
The further it ſwerves from the firſt <hi>Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi>
and Fundamentall <hi>Principles,</hi> the
faſter it declines, and haſtens towards <hi>Ruine;</hi>
So is it in the Church; The more ſhe devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ates,
and ſlips from her firſt <hi>Foundations,</hi> the
more ſhe growes into Diſtempers, and the
nearer ſhe comes to <hi>Deſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It hath been the wiſdome of all Princes, and Free States, of
former times, to carry a watchfull eye upon the growing <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venients</hi>
of their Kingdomes and Republiques; That, as evill
manners daily breed <hi>diſeaſes,</hi> ſo the continuall making, and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution
of good lawes ſhould daily be preſcribed as <hi>Remedies;</hi>
left, by too long neglect and ſufferance, the Body of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth
ſhould grow ſo <hi>foule</hi> with ſuperannuated evils, and
the humors waxe ſo <hi>prevalent,</hi> that the deſperateneſſe of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe
might enforce them to as <hi>deſperate</hi> a Remedy.</p>
            <p>It is no leſſe prudence and providence in thoſe that are appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
by the <hi>Supreme power</hi> (as under him) chiefe Governours and
<hi>Overſeers</hi> of the Church, to be very circumſpect; and, not onely
faithfully to exerciſe their <hi>Miniſteriall</hi> Function, by due and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<hi>preaching</hi> of the Goſpel; but likewiſe, diligently to diſcharge
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:110960:3"/>
their office in <hi>governing,</hi> that is, in making wholſome <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi>
and duly <hi>executing</hi> them; That the Inconveniences that
grow daily in the Church, may be daily <hi>rectified,</hi> leſt by too long
<hi>forbearance</hi> they gather head, and ſo become either <hi>incureable;</hi> or
elſe, capable of Remedy, with too great a <hi>loſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The naturall Affection I ſo dearly owe to this my native <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi>
(to which my ſoule alwayes hath, doth, and will for ever,
wiſh as much <hi>happineſſe</hi> as heaven can pleaſe to give) permits
me not to think our Church in ſo forlorne and deſperate a <hi>Caſe,</hi>
but that it may be <hi>capable</hi> of a wholſome Cure; Yet Senſe and
Reaſon (flying with the naturall <hi>wings</hi> of Love and Duty) bids
me feare, that thoſe unnaturall Humors, <hi>Pride, Negligence, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,
Schiſme,</hi> and (that Harbinger of Deſtruction) <hi>Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi>
have ſo long been gathering, and now <hi>ſetled</hi> in her, that ſhe
cannot, without long time, and much difficulty, (or elſe eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
providence and divine mercy) be reſtored; For the haſtning
whereof, accurſed be that unworthy <hi>Member</hi> that ſhall not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
the utmoſt of his endeavour, and diligence; and, not returne
the beſt of thoſe <hi>Abilities,</hi> he ſuckt from her in <hi>health,</hi> to her ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage,
in this her great and deplorable <hi>extremity</hi> of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper.</p>
            <p>The wearyed Phyſitian, (after his many fruitleſſe experiments
upon a <hi>conſuming</hi> Body) adviſes his drooping Patient to the <hi>place
of his birth,</hi> to draw that Ayre, he was firſt bred in: The likelyeſt
way to recover our <hi>languiſhing</hi> Church, is to reduce her to her
firſt <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> that ſhe may draw the <hi>breath</hi> of her firſt
Principles; from whence having made ſo long a <hi>journey,</hi> her
returne muſt take the <hi>longer</hi> time.</p>
            <p>The Phyſitian requires not his crazie Patient to take his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe
thither in a rumbling <hi>Coach,</hi> or a rude <hi>Waggon,</hi> (they are
too full of motion for a reſtleſſe body) nor to ride <hi>Poſte,</hi> (the
ſwiftneſſe of the paſſage makes too ſudden an alteration of the
Climate) but in an eaſie-going <hi>Litter,</hi> the ſlowneſſe of whoſe
pace might give him a <hi>graduall</hi> change of Ayre.</p>
            <p>The ſafeſt way to <hi>reduce</hi> our languiſhing Church to her firſt
Conſtitution, is to avoid all unnaturall <hi>Commotions,</hi> and <hi>violence</hi>
in her paſſage; and carefully to decline all <hi>ſudden alterations,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:110960:3"/>
which cannot be without imminent <hi>danger,</hi> and to uſe the <hi>peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableſt</hi>
meanes that may be, that nothing in her journey may <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt</hi>
her, and prove too prejudiciall to her <hi>journyes end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>diſeaſe</hi> of our diſtempered Church, (God be praiſed) hath
not as yet taken her principall parts; Her doctrine of Faith is
<hi>ſound;</hi> The Diſtemper onely lyes in her <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi>
which hath, theſe many yeeres, been breeding, and now,
broken forth, to the great diſhonour of (her <hi>Myſticall Head)</hi>
Chriſt Jeſus; to the unhappy interruption of her owne Peace,
<hi>(the Legacie of our bleſſed Saviour;)</hi> to the great diſquiet of our
gracious Soveraigne, <hi>(her Faiths Defender)</hi> to the ſharp afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
of his loyall Subjects, <hi>(her faithfull ſervants)</hi> and to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
ruine and deſtruction of this Kingdome, <hi>(the peacefull Palace
of her Glory.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. As for her <hi>Diſcipline;</hi> In the happy dayes of <hi>Edward</hi> the
ſixt, when all the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Rubbiſh and Trumpery was ſcavengerd
out of this (the new <hi>Reformed)</hi> Church, and the wholeſome <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>
of undubitable Truth was joyfully received into her gates,
(being for many yeeres clos'd with <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Error)</hi> the
piety and providence of her newly choſen <hi>Governours,</hi> (whoſe
ſpirituall Ab<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lities, and valour, were, after, characterd in their
owne <hi>blood)</hi> thought good, in the firſt place, to make Gods <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>
the ſubject of their holy Conſideration; To which end, they
met, and (finding in the Scriptures no expreſſe forme of <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall
Diſcipline</hi> in each particular, and therefore concluding,
it was left as a thing <hi>indifferent,</hi> to be inſtituted according to
the Conſtitutions of every Kingdome where Religion ſhould
be eſtabliſht) they adviſed, what <hi>Diſcipline</hi> might beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce
to the <hi>glory</hi> of God and the <hi>benefit</hi> of his people; They,
firſt, debated, and put to the queſtion, <hi>Whether the old Lytur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie
ſhould be corrected and purged,</hi> or <hi>whether a New ſhould be
contrived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cranmer,</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> a pious, moderate,
and learned <hi>Father</hi> of the Church, (and not long after a glorious
Martyr) finding, that the <hi>old Lyturgie</hi> had ſome things in it deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved
from the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, (though in many things corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted)
conceived it moſt fitting for the <hi>peace</hi> of the Church, not to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:110960:4"/>
ſavour ſo much of the ſpirit of <hi>contradiction,</hi> as utterly to aboliſh
it, becauſe the <hi>Papiſts</hi> uſed it; but, rather, enclined to have the old
Garden weeded, the Errors expunged; thereby, to gaine ſome
of the <hi>moderater</hi> ſort of that Religion to a <hi>Conformity:</hi> But <hi>Ridly</hi>
Biſhop of London, a man though very pious, yet of a <hi>quicker</hi> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,
and more violent, (and not many yeares after ſuffering <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome</hi>
too) enclined to a <hi>contrary</hi> Opinion, rather wiſhing a
totall <hi>abolition</hi> of the old Liturgie, and a new to be ſet up, leſt the
tender <hi>Conſciences</hi> of ſome ſhould be offended.</p>
            <p>The buſineſſe being thus controverted, it was at length voted
for the purging of the <hi>old;</hi> to which ſervice were appointed
<list>
                  <item>Doctor Cranmer <hi>Archbiſhop of</hi> Canterbury.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Goodrick Bishop of Ely.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Skip Bishop of Hereford.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Thirlby Bishop of Weſtminſter.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Day Bishop of Chicheſter.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Holbeck Bishop of Lincoln.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Ridley Bishop of Rocheſter.Martyr. after B. of London.</item>
                  <item>Doctor <hi>Cox</hi> King EDWARDS <hi>Almoner.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Doctor Taylor Deane of Lincoln. Martyr.</item>
                  <item>Doctor Heynes Deane of Exceter.</item>
                  <item>Doctor RedmanDeane of Weſtminſter.</item>
                  <item>Maſter <hi>Robinſon</hi> Archdeacon of <hi>Leyceſter.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Menſe <hi>Maio</hi> 1549. Anno Regni <hi>Edwardi</hi> ſexti tertie.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:110960:4"/>
Whereof three were famous <hi>Martyrs;</hi> and the reſt, men
of unqueſtionable <hi>ſanctity, ſoundneſſe,</hi> and <hi>learning;</hi> which,
being done, was authorized by <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> in that
bleſſed Kings reigne <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. and with a full <hi>Conſent</hi> received into
the Church of England, confirmed by divers Acts of Parl. in the
dayes of Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> King <hi>Iames,</hi> and King <hi>Charles,</hi> our now gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
Soveraigne, <hi>whom Almighty God long preſerve.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this eſtabliſht Diſcipline, had no ſooner <hi>being,</hi> but <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi>
(of which ſort the devill hath alwayes inſtruments to nip
the <hi>Plants</hi> of Religion in the Bud) whoſe number, daily ſince,
encreaſing, grew hotter and hotter in <hi>oppoſition,</hi> and ſtronger and
ſtronger in <hi>faction,</hi> being too long, for peace ſake, conniv'd at;
and, at laſt, too <hi>unſeaſonably,</hi> and <hi>violently</hi> oppoſed, inſomuch
that the <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> in theſe our late dayes, grew too powerfull for
the <hi>Remedy;</hi> ſo that the Diſtemper of our Church, in that reſpect,
is growne ſo high, that I feare <hi>Phlebotomy</hi> will rather produce a
further <hi>languiſhment</hi> (being already come to Madneſſe) then a
<hi>Cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, ſo far have the <hi>Enemies</hi> of this eſtabliſht Government
and Diſcipline, given way to their exorbitant and refractory <hi>Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi>
that they will neither allow the <hi>Matter,</hi> nor the <hi>Forme,</hi> nor
the Authority and teſtimony of the <hi>Compoſers.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Not the <hi>Matter;</hi> (though they cannot but acknowledge it,
in the generall, to be very good, yet) becauſe it was unſanctified
by <hi>ſuperſtitious</hi> lips.</item>
               <item>2. Not the <hi>Forme;</hi> becauſe ſet, and compoſed by <hi>Humane</hi>
Invention.</item>
               <item>3. Not the <hi>Compoſers;</hi> becauſe <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and ſo (though <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs</hi>
for the Cauſe of God and his true Religion) Members of
<hi>Antichriſt.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>1. As for their <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt the Matter; how ridicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous
they are, let <hi>Reaſon</hi> judge: Have not ſuperſtitious tongues,
and eyes, viewed and read the <hi>Scriptures</hi> in their very Originall
and purity? Shall therefore the Scriptures be diſallowed? Have
not ſuperſtitious perſons profaned our Churches with their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh
<hi>Doctrines, Sacraments</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies?</hi> and ſhall our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches
therefore be cryed downe, or ſhut againſt the <hi>Ordinances</hi> of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:110960:5"/>
God? becauſe thoſe Poets were <hi>Heatheniſh,</hi> was S. <hi>Paul</hi> afraid
to uſe their ſayings? Was the Spirit of God too blame, to <hi>endite</hi>
them? Good things, abuſed, worke evill effects upon the
<hi>abuſers;</hi> but loſe not their goodneſſe by the <hi>Abuſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As for their <hi>Exceptions</hi> againſt the Forme, being ſet, and
not conceived, the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Scriptures I hope will
anſwer.</p>
            <p>God the <hi>Father</hi> warrants it: God the <hi>Son</hi> preſcribes it: God
the <hi>holy Ghoſt</hi> allowes it.</p>
            <p>1. God the Father <hi>warrants</hi> it, in the Old Teſtament, at the
time of the <hi>Law,</hi> by his command to <hi>Moſes, Numb.</hi> 6. 21. where
he gives him a <hi>ſet forme</hi> and words to bleſſe the people, <hi>The Lord
bleſſe thee and keep thee, the Lord make his face to ſhine upon thee,
and be gracious unto thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. God the Sonne <hi>preſcribes</hi> it in the New Teſtament, in the
time of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> When S. <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt had taught his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
to <hi>pray,</hi> the Diſciples of Jeſus Chriſt (whoſe houſe was
called the houſe of Prayer) humbly requeſted the ſame <hi>boone</hi>
from him, who preſcribed them that <hi>Forme</hi> which he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly
uſed in the end of his Sermon, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. 9. which he inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
not as a <hi>Model,</hi> (as ſome would have it) but a very <hi>Prayer</hi>
it ſelfe, to be uſed in thoſe very words, as they were delivered
<hi>Luke.</hi> 11. 2. not, <hi>After this manner,</hi> but, <hi>when ye pray,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he will'd the ſame words to be uſed, is evident; For his
Diſciples would be taught, as <hi>Iohn</hi> taught his: And how were
they taught? S. <hi>Iohn</hi> taught them the <hi>words</hi> onely; he could not
give them the <hi>Spirit</hi> to make an <hi>extemporary deſcant</hi> upon them.
So that being a direct <hi>Set Forme,</hi> it warranted <hi>Set Formes,</hi> which
were uſed from the beginning of the <hi>Primitive Church;</hi> from
whence, this part of our <hi>Diſcipline</hi> had her originall.</p>
            <p>3. God the holy Spirit <hi>allowes</hi> it: Who dare queſtion, that the
<hi>holy Spirit</hi> inſpired S. <hi>Paul</hi> in all his Epiſtles, written to the
Churches? In all which Epiſtles he concludes with this one
Prayer, <hi>The grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. As for their <hi>exceptions</hi> againſt the Compoſers of this <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie,</hi>
who were no leſſe then holy Martyrs, (and by <hi>Fire-light</hi>
ſaw more <hi>Revelations</hi> then theſe Objectors did by day-light)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:110960:5"/>
men of approved learning and true piety: though ſome have im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence
and <hi>ſpirituall pride</hi> enough, to think their owne abilities
and <hi>inſpirations</hi> to flye a higher pitch; and Ignorance enough,
to acknowledge greater <hi>knowledge</hi> in themſelves, yet the moſt
humble, able, and truly ſanctified minds, have alwayes had <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdome</hi>
in ſo high reverence, that they conclude, that God that
made their blood the <hi>ſeed</hi> of the Church, and gave them the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
and honour <hi>to dye</hi> in the maintenance of the Truth, would
not permit that ſeed to bring forth ſuch <hi>darnel</hi> of ſuperſtition; or
them, to die guilty of thoſe <hi>Errors,</hi> they ſo reſolutely cryed down
with their <hi>dying blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. As for her government by <hi>Epiſcopacie,</hi> (the extirpation wherof
being a great addition to her <hi>Diſtemper)</hi> It hath as much or more
<hi>Ius Divinum</hi> to plead, then that, which endeavours to demoliſh
&amp; ſucceed it, <hi>Presbyterie;</hi> Both are <hi>but mentioned</hi> in the Scripture,
at large; but no <hi>particular</hi> Rules for the executing the office of
<hi>either;</hi> which, being left wholly as <hi>arbitrary,</hi> it reſts in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of the <hi>Supreme Magiſtrate</hi> (whom God hath conſtituted his
<hi>Vicegerent)</hi> to chooſe, and eſtabliſh, which may beſt be found
<hi>conſiſtent</hi> with the Conſtitutions of the Kingdome, and ſtand to
moſt advantage with the <hi>civil</hi> Government.</p>
            <p>But admit the Civil Government will ſtand with <hi>either?</hi>
When the Balances ſtand <hi>eavenly poiſed,</hi> the leaſt Grain turns it.
In things indifferent, the ſmalleſt <hi>circumſtance</hi> caſts it.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Iſland</hi> of Britaine (if we look back above 1400 yeares,
being a long <hi>Preſcription)</hi> when ſhe firſt received the Faith, was
then governed by King <hi>Lucius,</hi> whom God made a great <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
for reducing of this Kingdome from <hi>Paganiſme;</hi> who, ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to Rome, and accommodated from thence with two <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi>
and learned Divines, by their labours, and Gods aſſiſtance
upon them, planted the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> At the beginning of which plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation
<hi>Arch-Flamins</hi> and <hi>Flamins</hi> were put downe, and in their
roome <hi>Archbiſhops</hi> and <hi>Biſhops</hi> were introduced; which Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<hi>ſucceſſively</hi> continued, and flouriſht through the reigns
of many wiſe Princes, confirmed by many Acts of Parliament,
ſince the <hi>Reformation;</hi> exerciſed and approved by holy Martyrs;
and allowed of, as moſt fitting, untill the yeare of our Lord 1641.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:110960:6"/>
At which time, multitudes of the <hi>lower ſort</hi> of people, throughout
this Kingdome, petitioned, and tumultuouſly troubled the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament,</hi>
ſo that ſome of the Members, perchance according to their
<hi>inclination,</hi> and others, for quietneſſe ſake, conſented to the <hi>abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition</hi>
and <hi>extirpation</hi> of Epiſcopacy, the unadviz'd <hi>Contents</hi> of
their clamorous Petitions.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe Governments Hierarchicall and Presbyteriall
be <hi>indifferent;</hi> theſe Circumſtances, (Firſt, of the <hi>time,</hi> when
Epiſcopall Government began; Secondly, of the <hi>unintermiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive</hi>
continuance, for ſo many Ages; Thirdly, the <hi>credit of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi>
confirming and approving it) me thinks, ſhould caſt ſuch a
kind of <hi>neceſſity</hi> upon it, that the other (being an <hi>untry'd</hi> Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
and having no <hi>conſent</hi> or <hi>approbation</hi> from the Supreme
Magiſtrate; and, being onely cryed in by the <hi>Ignorant</hi> multitude,
affected to novelties and change) ſhould have no <hi>wiſe</hi> friend to
plead for it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>We reade in the Scriptures of</hi> Elders <hi>(which are members of
a</hi> Presbyterie) <hi>as it is written,</hi> Titus 1. 5. For this cauſe I left thee
in Creete that thou ſhouldeſt ſet in order things that are wanting,
and ordaine Elders in every City, as I had appointed thee. <hi>Alſo,</hi>
1 Pet. 5. 1. The Elders which are among you, I exhort, who am alſo
an Elder. <hi>By which it appears, that</hi> Titus <hi>had inſtructions to
ſet up a</hi> Presbyterie.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> You take the Scriptures by ſnatches: Had you read in <hi>Titus</hi> the
<hi>next</hi> verſe following but one, you would have had Saint <hi>Pauls
meaning</hi> with his words, <hi>viz. ver. 7. For a Biſhop muſt be blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,
as the ſteward of God, not ſelfe-willed, &amp;c.</hi> So that, it plainly
appeares, that <hi>Elders</hi> mentioned in the 5. verſe, are expounded
<hi>Biſhops</hi> in the 7. Or, had you compared Saint <hi>Peters firſt</hi> verſe
(before mentioned) with his <hi>fift</hi> in the ſame Chapter, you would
have found Elders no <hi>poſitive,</hi> but a <hi>relative</hi> word; no <hi>Office,</hi> but
a degree of <hi>Age. Ver. 5. Likewiſe the younger ſubmitting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
to the elder;</hi> the Apoſtle here ſhewing, what the behaviour
of the <hi>Elder</hi> Miniſters ſhould be towards God, and of the <hi>younger</hi>
towards them. So that if either of them had ſet up a <hi>Presbyterie,</hi>
it was ſuddenly pulled downe againe; and <hi>Epiſcopacie</hi> (which
you ſo much diſlike) placed in the roome.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:110960:6"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
We are ſo far from <hi>diſliking</hi> Biſhops, that where there is one,
we deſire there were twenty; nay that every Church in <hi>England</hi>
and <hi>Ireland</hi> had a ſeverall Biſhop; <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhops we diſlike,
<hi>Parochiall</hi> we allow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> How ſuddenly (to croſſe a ſetled and warranted eſtabliſhment)
your <hi>windmill</hi> fancies can make an <hi>alteration. Titus, c.</hi> 1. 5. had a
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand from S. <hi>Paul</hi> to ordain Elders in <hi>every City,</hi> (which he
interprets <hi>Biſhops)</hi> not in every <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>Pariſh;</hi> which <hi>Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance,</hi>
the Church of England hath punctually obſerved from the
<hi>Primitive</hi> times to <hi>this</hi> day. But you have refractory and gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaying
ſpirits, ſpirits of contradiction, that underſtand not the
Scriptures, but by your owne Interpretations; alwayes ſtirring,
but never ſetled; hating <hi>order,</hi> deſpiſing <hi>Government,</hi> and reſiſting
all <hi>Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But this <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> Government had her <hi>originall</hi> from Rome;
and being poyſoned in the <hi>Root,</hi> it cannot be wholſome in the
<hi>Branch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Ignorance is the <hi>mother</hi> of all Error. Your <hi>Chronologie</hi> failes
you: If you carefully ſearch <hi>Antiquities,</hi> you will find your <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi>
againſt it, a good <hi>Argument</hi> for it. I confeſſe Epiſcopacie
had her <hi>Originall</hi> partly from Rome; but, in thoſe dayes, when
we conformed according to the <hi>Church</hi> of Rome, the Church of
Rome conformed according to the <hi>Word</hi> of God. Rome was,
then, part of the <hi>Primitive</hi> Church, not being above 187. yeares
after Chriſt: The <hi>Biſhops</hi> of Rome were ſo far then from being
<hi>Antichriſts,</hi> that moſt of them were <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and dyed for
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But our Biſhops have too great <hi>Revenues;</hi> whereby, they are
occaſioned to <hi>Riot, pomp,</hi> and <hi>glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Thoſe Princely <hi>Benefactors</hi> (whoſe bountifull <hi>Pieties</hi> thought
nothing too much for Gods <hi>Ambaſſadours,</hi> and therefore enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
their <hi>Revenues</hi> ſo much) well knew their <hi>places</hi> and callings
requir'd it; whoſe gates were to be <hi>open</hi> to all commers; and
<hi>bread</hi> to be given to all that wanted. Their Places owe <hi>reliefe</hi>
to the fatherleſſe; <hi>comfort</hi> to the widow; <hi>ſupplies</hi> to the needy;
and <hi>ſuccour</hi> to all that are afflicted; and <hi>hoſpitality</hi> to all ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.
No, their great Revenues are greater <hi>Eye-ſores</hi> then <hi>Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences,</hi>
if not abuſed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:110960:7"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
But theſe great Revenues might have been <hi>decimated,</hi> and the
<hi>Tenth part</hi> might have ſufficiently maintained a <hi>preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi>
and the <hi>nine</hi> other parts might have been added to the Kings
<hi>Revenues,</hi> which <hi>would have made him the richeſt and moſt glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
King in Chriſtendome,</hi> and taken away the neceſſity of <hi>Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies</hi>
from the Subject.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> This is <hi>robbing Peter</hi> to <hi>pay Paul;</hi> beggering the <hi>Keyes</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich
the <hi>Sword,</hi> and the next way to bring a <hi>Curſe</hi> upon the King,
and all his people in generall, by a generall guilt of <hi>Sacriledge.</hi>
The <hi>Shewbread</hi> muſt not be eaten but upon more neceſſity then
(God be thanked) His Majeſty was at that time put to. <hi>The holy
Oyle</hi> muſt not be put unto a <hi>Civil</hi> uſe; But His Majeſties pious
and reſolute <hi>refuſall</hi> thereof hath in one word, fully and fairely
anſwered this Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But Biſhops have <hi>too abſolute</hi> a power, which gives them oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion
and opportunity to be <hi>tyrannicall,</hi> and to exerciſe an <hi>arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi>
Juriſdiction over their Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> From the <hi>beginning,</hi> I confeſſe, it was not ſo; neither ſtands it
with <hi>wiſdome</hi> or <hi>policy</hi> to ſuffer it to be ſo: For the Government
of the Church muſt have <hi>proportion</hi> with the Government of the
State: Government of <hi>ſeverall</hi> natures in one Nation, breeds <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion;</hi>
and that, <hi>ruine:</hi> We therefore being a <hi>mixt</hi> Monarchy,
neceſſarily require a <hi>mixture</hi> likewiſe in the Hierarchy; which
excludes all <hi>arbitrary</hi> power.</p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>abſolute</hi> Monarchy, and an <hi>unlimited</hi> Hierarchy are
apt to fall into the diſtemper of <hi>Tyrannie;</hi> and Democracie and a
<hi>parity</hi> in Government is as apt to run into the diſeaſe of <hi>Tumult;</hi>
but of the two evils, Tyrannie is the <hi>leaſt,</hi> by how much it is the
eaſier to be <hi>cured.</hi> A monſter with <hi>one</hi> head is ſooner overcome
then a <hi>Hidra</hi> with many. If our Hierarchy hath ſlipt into this <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity,</hi>
it is great wiſdome and reaſon for a Parliament to
<hi>rectifie</hi> it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But the King having the <hi>ſole</hi> Election of Biſhops, and ſo much
favouring them, will hardly conſent to the abridgement of their
<hi>power</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe;</hi> ſo that, being his <hi>Creatures,</hi> their power
will be upheld by him, to the end that upon any <hi>difference</hi> betwixt
him and his people, they may be the more able to uphold him,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:110960:7"/>
and ready to make a ſtrong <hi>party</hi> for him; ſo that the more their
<hi>power</hi> is weakned, the leſſe his <hi>party</hi> will be prevalent, whereby,
his <hi>Prerogative</hi> may want Advocates, and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
no enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> His Majeſty, by his yeelding to the <hi>Bill</hi> of taking away their
<hi>Votes</hi> in Parliament, hath given a ſufficient Earneſt of a further
<hi>Moderation</hi> of their power; and no queſtion, was, and will be
ready to hearken to this or ſuch like humble and reaſonable <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
(for the extirpating this jelouſie) <hi>viz.</hi> That when any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
<hi>dyes,</hi> or is tranſlated, he would give liberty to the whole
<hi>Clergie</hi> and <hi>Freeholders</hi> of thoſe Dioceſſes to chooſe, nominate &amp;
preſent <hi>foure</hi> learned and religious Divines, moſt <hi>unblameable</hi> in
life and doctrine, able for <hi>government,</hi> and diligent in <hi>preaching:</hi>
Of which foure, His Majeſty to prick <hi>one,</hi> which may be conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<hi>Biſhop of the Dioces;</hi> By which meanes, both His Majeſty
and His People, having an <hi>intereſt</hi> in him, he will be equally en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged;
who, in caſes of <hi>difference,</hi> may become rather a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator</hi>
then <hi>Partaker:</hi> and, receiving juſt power from the <hi>King,</hi>
may execute it as uprightly amongſt his <hi>people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>But they are</hi> Lords, <hi>and lord it over Gods</hi> Inheritance: <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,</hi>
1 Pet. 5. 3. <hi>forbids it,</hi> Be not Lords over Gods inheritance:
<hi>and Chriſt,</hi> Luk. 2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 25. <hi>ſayes,</hi> The Kings of the earth exerciſe
Lordſhip, but it ſhall not be ſo with you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Our Biſhops were Lords, as they were <hi>Peeres</hi> of the Land, and
as Peeres, they had <hi>Votes</hi> in Parliament; which, being <hi>taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi>
they are no more, now, then what the dignity of their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
and their owne Merits make them. As for that place in S.
<hi>Peter,</hi> thus it is meant; <hi>Ye ſhall not be Lords over Gods inheritance,</hi>
that is, Tyrants; <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Rulers</hi> being at that time none but
<hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> whoſe tyrannie made the very name
of <hi>Lord,</hi> terrible, and odious: So that, in that place, by Lordſhip
is certainly meant <hi>Tyrannie.</hi> Neither can this imply a <hi>Parity</hi> in
our Church; for without a <hi>Superiority,</hi> and <hi>Inferiority,</hi> there
can be no Government: A Parity cannot be conſidered in <hi>order</hi> of
Government; but, onely, in the <hi>work</hi> of the Miniſtry. In this, all
are <hi>fellow labourers;</hi> In the other, ſome <hi>command,</hi> and ſome <hi>obeye</hi>
S. <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> had an eſpeciall <hi>command</hi> and charge over
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:110960:8"/>
other Miniſters. As for that place in S. <hi>Luke,</hi> which you all edge,
The Diſciples ſtriving <hi>who ſhould be the greateſt among them,</hi> our
bleſſed Saviours anſwer was to this effect, <hi>Let Kings exerciſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer
and authority over their vaſſals,</hi> (as indeed their tyrannie
made them little better) but it ſhall be otherwiſe with you: You
are all <hi>fellow-ſervants</hi> to me, that am your chiefe <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Biſhop
of your ſoules;</hi> whilſt I am here, all ſuperiority lyes extinct:
Chriſt was then the onely <hi>Governour,</hi> and the <hi>Root</hi> of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
was in him: But at his departure, he gave <hi>ſome to be Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
ſome to be Paſtors, &amp;c.</hi> and yet all thoſe degrees were <hi>equall</hi>
in reſpect of the <hi>work:</hi> He himſelfe ſaid, <hi>Ye call me Lord, and ſo I
am,</hi> and yet, <hi>Luk. 22. 27. I am among you as he that ſerveth:</hi>
whereby it manifeſtly appeares, he intended a parity of the <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers</hi>
in reſpect of the <hi>worke,</hi> not a parity in the <hi>government</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
of the <hi>workers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Biſhops (whoſe office is to promote <hi>Religion,</hi> and to advance
the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> (as is pretended) and to encourage <hi>Preaching</hi> as the
ordinary meanes conducing thereunto) are ſo far from <hi>ſo</hi> doing,
that inſtead thereof, they ſilence godly <hi>Miniſters,</hi> and put downe
<hi>weekly Lectures,</hi> which were ſet up at the proper <hi>charges</hi> and the
<hi>piety</hi> of the people; and to the great <hi>eſtabliſhment</hi> of true Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Here lyes a <hi>Myſterie;</hi> being the moſt crafty advantage the
devilever took of <hi>popular</hi> piety.</p>
            <p>Admit the <hi>piety</hi> of the honeſt hearted People was the firſt <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi>
to theſe weekly Lectures, how was that piety <hi>abuſed,</hi> by
thoſe weekly <hi>Lecturers?</hi> They were <hi>choſen</hi> by the people; their
<hi>maintenance</hi> (conſiſting moſt of Gratuities) came from the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
which ebbed or flowed according as their <hi>Lunatick</hi> doctrines
wrought upon the people. Thoſe Lecturers (whoſe whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
thus proceeded from the people) muſt for their owne
better lively hoods <hi>pleaſe</hi> the people: And what more pleaſing
to the people then the preaching of <hi>Liberty?</hi> and how ſhould
Liberty be enlarged, if not peeced with <hi>Prerogative?</hi> Then down
goes <hi>Authority,</hi> and up goes <hi>Priviledge;</hi> Downe goes the <hi>Booke,</hi>
and up goes the <hi>Spirit;</hi> Downe goes <hi>Learning,</hi> and up goes <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation;</hi>
who gaining credit in the weak opinions of the <hi>vulgar,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:110960:8"/>
grew the <hi>Seminaries</hi> of all Ignorance, and the <hi>nurſing fathers</hi> of
all Rebellion. Theſe are thoſe <hi>godly</hi> Lecturers that Biſhops put
downe, who never loſt themſelves ſo much, as in not ſetting up
<hi>better</hi> and more <hi>orthodox</hi> in their roomes, which had taken away
the ground of this Objection.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Our Biſhops being <hi>proud, idle, covetous,</hi> and <hi>Popiſhly</hi> affected,
are therefore fit to be extirpated.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Admit ſome be ſo; therefore, ſuch, among them, as are
<hi>humble, diligent, charitable,</hi> and enemies to <hi>Popery,</hi> periſh? Shall
they that are <hi>bad,</hi> have more power to pull downe a ſetled Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,
then they that be <hi>good,</hi> to keep it up? Did <hi>Moſes,</hi> the
man of God, extirpate the Government of <hi>Prieſthood</hi> becauſe
<hi>Aaron</hi> had a hand in the peoples <hi>Idolatry?</hi> Or, will you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take
that the Elders in a <hi>Presbyteriall</hi> Government ſhall be all
faultleſſe? Let the <hi>guilty</hi> receive their reſpective puniſhments,
and <hi>let others take their office:</hi> But the <hi>innocent</hi> to ſuffer with the
<hi>guilty,</hi> is a point of high <hi>injuſtice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But admit this Government by Biſhops, had nothing to plead
for it, neither <hi>preſcription,</hi> nor <hi>continuance</hi> without Intermiſſion,
nor the <hi>Authority</hi> of Parliaments in all Ages, yet conſidering it
is, now, a Government, in <hi>Being,</hi> it ſeemes not conſonant to
Reaſon, or policy to <hi>extirpate</hi> it, or take it away, before an <hi>other</hi>
Government be pitcht upon. To pull downe one maine <hi>Pillar,</hi>
before another be made fit to ſupply the place, and to <hi>ſupport</hi> the
roome, is the next way to pull the <hi>Roofe</hi> upon our heads: Hath
not Epiſcopacie been long <hi>voted</hi> downe? And is not the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly,
at this time, divided and in controverſie, nay puzzled what
Government to ſet up in the <hi>roome</hi> of it? By which means, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
is adminiſtred to all <hi>diſorder,</hi> Liberty lyes open to all <hi>Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes,
Sects,</hi> and <hi>Hereſies,</hi> and Sectaries grow bold to vent their
giddy headed opinions without controlment, confirming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
in their owne <hi>Errors,</hi> infecting others with their new fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled
and itching <hi>doctrines,</hi> the nature whereof is (like a <hi>Tetter)</hi>
to run, till it over-run the whole <hi>Body.</hi> (Have not our eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held
all this?) which if theſe unſetled times ſhould long conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue,
(as God forbid) would gather ſuch head, and ſtrengthen this
our <hi>confuſed</hi> Kingdome, that if her iſſue of blood were <hi>ſtopt</hi> in one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:110960:9"/>
place, it would <hi>break forth</hi> in another; and, like <hi>Hercules</hi> his
Monſter, if one head were <hi>ſtruck off,</hi> another would <hi>ariſe,</hi> to the
utter confuſion of the true Proteſtant Religion, which already
begins to be the leaſt part of this tottering Kingdoms profeſſion,
and rather conniv'd at, then exerciz'd by ſome. Are not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints
preferd againſt <hi>Browniſts</hi> and <hi>Separatiſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See a book Intituled,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heſumme of a <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> at <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 11. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>43.</note> unheard? Nay,
are not men <hi>afraid</hi> to complain againſt them for feare of <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
Have not profeſt Anabaptiſts challenged our Miniſters to
<hi>diſpute</hi> with them in their owne open Churches? Have not their
diſputations been <hi>permitted,</hi> nay, unadviſedly <hi>undertaken</hi> by ſome
of our Miniſters, (who themſelves are though little better)
wherein they have made many <hi>Proſelites,</hi> and left many of the
vulgar (who judge the victory to the moſt words) <hi>indifferent?</hi>
Have they not after their diſputations retired into their Innes, and
private Iodgings, accompanyed with many of their <hi>Auditors,</hi> and
all joyned together in their <hi>extemporary</hi> prayers for a bleſſing
upon their late <hi>Exerciſe?</hi> How often hath <hi>Bow-river</hi> (which
they lately have baptiz'd <hi>New Iordan)</hi> been witneſſe to their
prophanations? How many daily make their private <hi>meetings,</hi>
and aſſemble in the City of London to exerciſe their <hi>Miniſtery?</hi>
How many have been convicted of Blaſphemy, and yet unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht?
How many times have their <hi>witneſſes</hi> been taken againſt
ſome of our moſt learned and religious Miniſters? for which,
ſome, are <hi>plundered,</hi> ſome <hi>ſequeſtred,</hi> and ſome <hi>impriſoned:</hi> How
many of our Miniſters whoſe ſeverity proceeded formerly againſt
Fornicators, Adulterers, Drunkards, Swearers, and ſuch like,
are now undone upon their <hi>revengefull</hi> witneſſes and teſtimony,
appearing now (for the better colouring of their malice) <hi>well
affected</hi> to the Cauſe? All which in time will ſo encourage all
Sects, Factions, Hypocrites, and make Hereſie ſo bold, &amp; ſtrong
in this Kingdome, that the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> will be (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
the deteſtable name of <hi>Popery)</hi> even turned out of doores for
company, or at leaſt ſo little favoured, that it will be forced to
<hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rowd</hi> it ſelfe in corners, as thoſe Sectaries did, before theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
were.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> I, but when things are <hi>ſetled,</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> done upon the <hi>Popiſh</hi>
Faction, theſe <hi>Sectaries</hi> with their Sects will vaniſh like the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:110960:9"/>
Miſt before the <hi>mid day</hi> ſun, and a true <hi>reformed</hi> Religion will be
eſtabliſht to us and our Poſterity.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> You ſeeme by this Objection but a young <hi>State Phyſitian,</hi> and
a meere <hi>novice</hi> in the curing of a diſeaſe of this <hi>nature.</hi> In ſome
caſes, where the <hi>undiſturbed</hi> humors keep their bounds, diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers
are quickly <hi>evaporated,</hi> and being ſcatterd through the whole
body, every part <hi>breathes</hi> out ſome, and Nature (being able to
truckle with the <hi>diſeaſe)</hi> by her owne power, relieves her ſelfe;
and, in a ſhort time, <hi>rectifies</hi> the Body: But upon a <hi>continuall</hi>
confluence, and gathering head of <hi>lawleſſe</hi> humors, ſhe is ſo
weakned; that ſhe hath no power to reſiſt, and leſſe heart to ſtrug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle
with her <hi>enemy,</hi> but is forced to yeeld: But the time you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixe
for the ſubduing of theſe numerous <hi>Sects,</hi> is, firſt, when all
things are <hi>ſetled,</hi> ſecondly, when the Land is <hi>cleared</hi> of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts.</p>
            <p>1. For the firſt, It is all one as if you had ſaid, <hi>When the body
is in good health, you will eaſily find a cure.</hi> A rare Phyſitian! In
the meane while, you will connive at this continued <hi>confluence</hi>
of humors, which makes it at length incureable.</p>
            <p>2. As for the ſecond: Take heed while ye goe about to cure a
<hi>Fever,</hi> you run not the Body Politick into a <hi>Dropſie,</hi> with too
much <hi>Phlebotomie.</hi> But you will firſt cleare the Kingdome of
<hi>Papiſts:</hi> And who be they? In your Accompt, all ſuch as ſtand
for <hi>Epiſcopall</hi> Government, (a Government coetaneous with
this our almoſt out-dated Religion) All ſuch as approve of the
<hi>Book of Common Prayer,</hi> (a Forme eſtabliſht by many Acts of
<hi>Proteſtant</hi> Parliaments) All ſuch as are paſſively obedient, and
loyall to his Majeſty (a duty commanded by Gods own mouth.)
Of the Clergie, all ſuch as will not preach for <hi>blood,</hi> (although
Miniſters of the Goſpel of <hi>Peace.)</hi> All ſuch as will not take the
<hi>Covenant,</hi> to ſuppreſſe Biſhops, (although they have formerly
ſworn <hi>canonicall obedience</hi> to their Ordinary) All ſuch as wil not
encourage Subjects to <hi>reſiſt</hi> the power of their naturall Prince,
(although having taken the <hi>Oath of Allegeance,</hi> and the late <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.)</hi>
And to conclude, all that have not <hi>contributed</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly,
bountifully, and continually to this Warre; and in a
word, that have any <hi>conſiderable</hi> Eſtates to pick a hole in: If all
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:110960:10"/>
               <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Sectaries</hi> be not ſuppreſt till then, we are like to have a
comfortable <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in caſe, you onely meane ſuch <hi>Papiſts</hi> as owne, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
the <hi>doctrine</hi> of the Church of Rome; Tell me, what
courſe would you take with them?</p>
            <p>Either you muſt <hi>baniſh</hi> them, or <hi>diſinherit</hi> them, or <hi>take away</hi>
their lives.</p>
            <p>1. If <hi>baniſh</hi> them; It muſt be done, either <hi>with</hi> the Kings
conſent, or <hi>againſt</hi> it; If <hi>againſt</hi> it, you reſiſt the power, and <hi>he
that reſiſteth ſhall receive damnation, Rom.</hi> 13. If <hi>with</hi> it, you
make the King guilty of <hi>perjury,</hi> who hath ſworne to <hi>protect all</hi>
his Subjects in his <hi>Coronation Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. If <hi>diſinherit</hi> them; It muſt be done, either <hi>according</hi> to the
known Lawes of the Kingdome, or <hi>againſt</hi> them; According to
the Lawes, ye cannot; for there is no Law for it. If againſt them,
you tranſgreſſe what you pretend to maintaine in all your <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. If <hi>take away</hi> their lives, It muſt be done, either <hi>for</hi> a Cauſe,
or <hi>without</hi> a Cauſe; If for a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> ſhew it, that the world may
be ſatisfied: If without a <hi>Cauſe,</hi> you are guilty of <hi>murther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which courſe ſoever ye take, you have not Chriſt for your <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample,</hi>
who quietly ſuffered the two <hi>Caeſars,</hi> being <hi>Idolaters,</hi> not
onely to poſſeſſe that Kingdome, but to <hi>uſurp</hi> it, becauſe God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
them, and <hi>permiſſively</hi> placed them there: When the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
askt our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Didſt not thou ſow good wheat?
Whence commeth it that there be tares?</hi> His anſwer was, <hi>The evil
one hath done it.</hi> His pleaſure being demanded, whether they
ſhould <hi>weed</hi> them up? his Reply was, No, <hi>Let them alone untill
the harveſt,</hi> and then he would ſeparate them.</p>
            <p>A good deed may be ill done, when either againſt <hi>command,</hi> or
without <hi>warrant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though God hath permitted the <hi>evill one</hi> to plant Papiſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
us, yet he hath not authorized us to <hi>root</hi> them up, nor yet to
take the lives of any, untill their actions come within the danger
and compaſſe of the eſtabliſht <hi>Lawes</hi> of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> We have preſidents for the <hi>rooting out</hi> of Idolaters in the
Scriptures; which warrant us to doe the like.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:110960:10"/>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label>
You finde it no where, but in the time of the <hi>Law;</hi> at which
time, God <hi>immediately</hi> commanded it; which kind of Warrants
are now ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Again, In the time of the Law, ſome were accompted <hi>Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi>
And ſtrangers had not the priviledges that <hi>brethren</hi> have<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <hi>Vſury was lawfull to be taken of ſtrangers,</hi> not of brethren: Now,
in the times of the Goſpel, Chriſt hath made us all <hi>Brethren,</hi>
and called us by his own name, <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> and what was <hi>law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,</hi>
then, to be done to ſtrangers, is <hi>unwarrantable,</hi> now, to be
done to Chriſtians. <hi>We are brethren.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Then Proteſtantiſme and Popery may be <hi>conſiſtent</hi> in one
Kingdom, and Gods name may be harmeleſly prophaned with
<hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>ſuperiſtition,</hi> in the ſame place, where it is <hi>truly</hi> and
ſincerely worſhipt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſ. </seg>
               </label> Your inference is not good. It is one thing for a Prince to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect</hi>
his ſubjects; and an other to be <hi>partaker</hi> with them, or to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
of their <hi>ſuperſtitions.</hi> Kings cannot enforce Conſciences,
though pitcht upon a falſe Religion: All that Magiſtrates can do
againſt them (unleſſe for <hi>Seducing,</hi> which a particular Statute made
<hi>Treaſon)</hi> is to puniſh their <hi>purſes,</hi> for not obſerving his <hi>Statutes</hi>
reſpectively, or for exerciſing their Religion <hi>contrary</hi> to his
Lawes, But well it were if ſuch a <hi>neceſſity</hi> of Connivance had no
ſuch ſubject to work upon.</p>
            <p>How happy had it been for this unlucky kingdom, if his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties
moſt prudent and pious <hi>offer,</hi> two yeare ſince, propounded
to us, had been accepted in this <hi>particular, That all the Children
of his ſubjects of that Religion, ſhould be taken from them, and edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated
in the Religion of the Church of England?</hi> By which means,
the whole Kingdom, in a ſhort ſpace of time, would have been
peaceably reduced to an <hi>Vnity</hi> in Doctrine; And, if the ſame courſe
were taken with othe Strectaryes, an <hi>Vniformity</hi> in Diſcipline alſo.
But our Kingdom muſt not expect an univerſall and through Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation
in all particulars, till Catechiſmes be more ſtrictly
uſed, and the entercourſe of Embaſſadours (which cannot ſimply
be avoyded) and Legers be reſtrained; and ſtrict ſtatutes made
and executed againſt <hi>ſectaries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to returne to our firſt matter. Admit <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> were a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:110960:11"/>
Government, accidentally inconvenient, and that a <hi>more fitting</hi>
Government, were diſcovered, prepared and made <hi>ready</hi> to be
ſet up, It would be but a <hi>new untryed</hi> Government, and not expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally
known what <hi>proportion</hi> it would beare without <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall</hi>
Conſtitutions. A horſe may be well metled, and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
and every way commendable for the <hi>ſaddle;</hi> yet not draw
well in a Coach or <hi>Chariot:</hi> A great part of our <hi>Common-Law</hi>
is bu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lt upon the <hi>Caſes</hi> of Biſhops, inſomuch that if that Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
be changed, there muſt be a neceſſary <hi>alteration</hi> of many
Lawes of the land; And what <hi>incovenience</hi> may ariſe from ſuch
an Alteration, I leave to the Judgment of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> being not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy
of ſome Conſideration.</p>
            <p>But let theſe things be accompted not <hi>Inconveniencyes,</hi> and
that the Hierarchicall Government is fit to be <hi>demoliſhed,</hi> either
for the abuſe of it, by ſome few exorbitant <hi>Prelates,</hi> or for the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes
that follow, in reſpect of it <hi>ſelf,</hi> in that it adminiſters ſuch
occaſion of <hi>offence,</hi> yet the <hi>too ſudden</hi> Execution of a buſines of ſo
great <hi>aconſequence,</hi> and concernment, gives a livelyer teſtimony of
<hi>paſſion</hi> then diſcretion, (if polititions may have credit) and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours
of <hi>extremity,</hi> (which is oppoſite to all virtue,) and too
much raſhneſſe, the <hi>diſtemper</hi> of all ſerious and honorable under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings:
Too ſudden an Alteration in matters of <hi>ſmall</hi> moment,
paſſes not without ſome inconvenience; but, in things of ſuch a
nature, as a <hi>Government,</hi> nay a <hi>Church</hi> government too (the <hi>nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery</hi>
of the whole kingdoms happineſſe or miſery) it cannot be
without <hi>imminent</hi> danger; but the <hi>ſudden</hi> alteration of a <hi>funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall</hi>
government, of the Church (which neceſſarily carryes
the ſtate with it) threatens, nay brings no leſſe then <hi>unavoydable
ruine</hi> to both.</p>
            <p>A Raſhnes, too much (we feare) reliſhing of private ends to
demoliſh that government in <hi>twelve moneths,</hi> which hath been
ſetting up and maintained by as wiſe generations as ours, above
<hi>foureteen hundred yeares.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How happy had it been for this (at that time proſperous, but
now miſerable) kingdom, had we taken the advantage of (that
greateſt <hi>bleſſing,</hi> that ever gracious Prince confered upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull
Subjects) the <hi>Trienniall Parliament,</hi> wherein, we
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:110960:11"/>
might every 3 years have inſpected this <hi>new recoverd</hi> Kingdome,
and kept it alwayes in a perfect <hi>Criſis,</hi> the approaching Terror
whereof, would not have afforded popular evils ſo long a time,
or liberty to <hi>root</hi> themſelves or gather <hi>head</hi> againſt the peace and
welfare of our happy Government; through the benefit where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
we might have taken an advantageous leiſure and mature deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beration
to <hi>ripen</hi> every Bill, and, by <hi>degrees,</hi> to rectifie every <hi>non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ag'd</hi>
Crievance, and indeed, what happineſſe was there, which we
had not then an offerd <hi>opportunity</hi> to bring upon this (now) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy
Land? The Government of the <hi>State,</hi> as in many things,
it was reduced into an excellent <hi>temper;</hi> ſo, queſtionleſſe, (had
not this unnaturall difference interpoſed) it had in all things (by
the continued goodneſſe and favour of His Sacred Majeſty) been
perfected, to the comfort of us, and the happineſſe of ſucceeding
<hi>Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Government of the <hi>Church</hi> likewiſe might, by the vertue
of the granted <hi>Trienniall,</hi> been narrowly and exactly ſearcht into;
The <hi>Governours</hi> ſtrictly obſerved; The <hi>Bad</hi> turned out, and chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
for <hi>better;</hi> They that deſerved puniſhment, puniſht accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
to their <hi>miſdemeanours;</hi> Others, leſſe offending through
ſome neglect, <hi>reproved</hi> and <hi>checkt;</hi> and, upon no amendment, the
next <hi>Trienniall,</hi> proceeded againſt accordingly.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Fig-tree</hi> was not preſently cut downe, <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Branch,</hi>
but ſuffered till <hi>another yeare;</hi> And puniſhments before an <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi>
are too raſhly and ſeverely inflicted.</p>
            <p>Thus by this graduall and Trienniall Courſe, Mercy and Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice
would have <hi>incorporated;</hi> the Government of the Church
had been <hi>eſtabliſht;</hi> the peace of this Kingdome had been <hi>ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi>
the bad Governours had been <hi>rectified,</hi> or <hi>removed;</hi> the
good, <hi>encouraged</hi> and <hi>honoured;</hi> and <hi>Peace and Truth had kiſt
each other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the multitudes of theſe our nationall <hi>ſins</hi> were too great,
to permit ſo great a <hi>Bleſſing</hi> on this Nation, as the benefit of this
<hi>Trienniall Parliament.</hi> God ſuffered <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>ſee the holy
Land,</hi> but for the tranſgreſſions of the people, <hi>not to poſſeſſe it:</hi>
God ſhewed us a <hi>glimpſe</hi> of that mercy (which our ſins made us
unworthy to enjoy) and ſnatcht it from us. In which reſpect, we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:110960:12"/>
are now left to our owne <hi>wayes,</hi> and governed by our owne <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions;</hi>
and (what is worſe) we are neither penitent for our
<hi>nationall</hi> ſins, nor our <hi>owne;</hi> nor (what is worſt of all) ſenſible
of Gods <hi>Iudgements,</hi> nor our owne <hi>miſeries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How often have our Moderne Miniſters in their <hi>unmeditated</hi>
prayers, before the open <hi>Congregation,</hi> given God <hi>joyfull</hi> thanks
for theſe bleſſed times!<note place="margin">Eccleſ. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Whereas (if their <hi>hearts had not been ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
to utter any things</hi> before God) they might have rather petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned
for a <hi>removall</hi> of theſe his terrible judgements: How often
have they prayed for the <hi>continuance</hi> of theſe happy dayes!
whereas,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> had not their <hi>mouthes been raſh,</hi> they might better have
<hi>deprecated</hi> thoſe miſeries. How often have they in their <hi>Sermons,</hi>
blaſphemouſly challenged God (upon the forfeiture of his Juſtice)
to crowne their <hi>Cauſe</hi> with Victory! How often, inſtead of
<hi>wholſome</hi> doctrine, have they delivered ſuch reports as their
Conſciences knew <hi>Fables,</hi> and were before next Sabboth <hi>Lyes
upon Record?</hi> How often have they preached downe <hi>Subjection</hi>
to Princes, and encouraged the <hi>Sword</hi> to grow warme in the
blood of Chriſtians? How often have they Articled againſt Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxe,
able, and learned Divines; and crowded themſelves
into their Livings, who upon my certaine knowledge (ſome of
them) can neither make true <hi>Latine,</hi> nor write good <hi>Engliſh;</hi>
and then, lay their <hi>preferment</hi> upon the wiſdome of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?
How many children above a yeare old (becauſe their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
are ſuſpected to be loyall to their Prince) continue <hi>unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd?</hi>
many pariſhes can witneſſe. How long time is it ſince the
laſt <hi>Sacrament of the Lords Supper</hi> was adminiſtred, let the people
tell, if their memories be ſo good; and then, the Elements deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verd
in their owne <hi>new deviſed</hi> words. Theſe are now the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel of <hi>Peace:</hi> Theſe the Miniſters of this
<hi>bleſſed Reformation:</hi> Theſe the men that muſt pull downe <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt</hi>
out of his ſeat, and ſet up <hi>Chriſt Ieſus</hi> in his throne: Nay,
rather, theſe are they that for filthy lucre carry men about with
<hi>divers</hi> and ſtrange <hi>doctrines:</hi> Theſe are the men that in former
times <hi>ſeparated</hi> themſelves, <hi>ſenſuall, having not the Spirit.</hi> Theſe
are they that <hi>deſpiſe</hi> dominion, and <hi>ſpeak evill</hi> of dignities: Theſe
are ſuch as have gone the way of <hi>Cain,</hi> and run greedily after the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:110960:12"/>
error of <hi>Balaam</hi> for reward; and have periſhed in the <hi>gaine-ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi>
of <hi>Core:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 12.</note> Theſe are <hi>ſpyes</hi> in your feaſts of charity, feeding them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<hi>without feare;</hi> clouds, that are without <hi>Water</hi> carried about
with the <hi>winde;</hi>
               <note place="margin">13.</note> rageing <hi>waves</hi> of the Sea, fomeing out their own
<hi>ſhame,</hi> to whom is reſerved the <hi>blackneſſe</hi> of darkneſſe for ever.</p>
            <p>Is not this a bleſſed <hi>Prieſthood?</hi> Are not theſe rare <hi>materialls</hi>
for a hopefull Presbytery? Fit governours for the <hi>houſe of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Are not the two great <hi>Nurſeryes</hi> of this kingdom like to flour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh;
when the chiefe <hi>Plants</hi> are pulled up by the roots, and onely
theſe Crabſtocks ſuffered to proſper, and beare their own <hi>naturall</hi>
fruit? Our fathers have eaten the <hi>Grapes,</hi> and their childrens teeth
will be <hi>ſet on edge.</hi> They that have been the Pillars of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion
are <hi>hewen down,</hi> and our falling Church is <hi>ſhored up</hi> with theſe
inconſiderable <hi>ſpars.</hi> They that grappled with, and foyld the
ſtouteſt <hi>Champions</hi> of the Church of Rome, are <hi>impriſoned;</hi> want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
both <hi>bread</hi> and <hi>liberty;</hi> And ſuch as neither did, nor could, nor
durſt appeare in ſuch a <hi>quarrel,</hi> are crownd with their <hi>Reward:</hi>
They whoſe learning and orthodox piety made England the <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
of nations,</hi> and the <hi>envy</hi> of forraigne kingdoms, are now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced
and ruined; and thoſe, that learning made not capable of a
<hi>Degree,</hi> advanced and honoured to the great diſhonour of this
kingdom.</p>
            <p>Nor can I heare forget, how much this ſtaggering Church of
England owes to her pious and religious <hi>Nurſing Father,</hi> and
her faiths royall <hi>Defender,</hi> our gracious Soveraigne; whoſe wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,
moderation and tender piety (amongſt other of his princely
vertues) hath ſo manifeſty ſhowed it ſelf; in not following the
example of thoſe, whom my heart bleeds to call his Enemyes;
and blazing the <hi>new</hi> Miniſtry of this kingdom, as they have done
the <hi>old?</hi> Had his provoked paſſion publiſht a <hi>Century</hi> to the eye
of all the world, of thoſe morall vices, hideous blaſphemies, infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities
and faylings of the Clergy of the <hi>one party,</hi> as they did on
<hi>the other,</hi> how would the Church of Rome, and all the <hi>Enemies</hi> of
the Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, have hiſſed and derided our Religion?
that, by the generall Confeſſion both of Prince, and people, had
ſuch <hi>Monſters</hi> to adorne it? How would forraigne Chriſtians
have been frighted at the very name of the <hi>Church of England?</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:110960:13"/>
How would the ſtile of Proteſtant have become the <hi>Obloquy,</hi> and
<hi>Byword</hi> of all Religions: It was not for want of <hi>matter:</hi> Report
would have coynd enough, beſides that, which, perchance, would
have made the <hi>truer hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor was it <hi>ſcarcity</hi> of pen-men, to paint their actions to the life:
Oxford had &amp; yet hath Pens, ſharp enough, &amp; Inck that wanted no
<hi>Gall:</hi> Nor can I conceive how ſuch nimble, active, and ſuch ſalik
<hi>fancyes</hi> here could have forborne it, had not the wiſdom &amp; provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
of his Sacred Majeſty laid upon them his <hi>reſtraining</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er:
By which it evidently appeares to thoſe that are not obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natly
and malitionſly blinded with the darkneſſe of reſolved Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,
that his Majeſties ſolemne <hi>Vowes,</hi> and ſerious <hi>Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi>
for the maintaining the honour of the true Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
agree with his moſt pious <hi>Intentions,</hi> and publiſhed <hi>Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions:</hi>
Had his ſecret affections been <hi>warpt,</hi> or the l<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt degree <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering</hi>
from the Church of England, or any whit <hi>inclineing</hi> to the
Romiſh ſuperſtition; had the imaginations of his heart intended
ſecretly an <hi>introduction</hi> of the popiſh Religion, how could his
new deſigne been better animated, then by an inward <hi>diſlike</hi> of the
Proteſtant Religion, &amp; how could that diſlike have been better fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented
and encouraged, then by the Advantage, the juſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage
taken of the generall <hi>corruption</hi> of her Miniſtry?</p>
            <p>But the wiſdom and tenderneſſe of his Piety ſtands <hi>ſilent,</hi> in
this behalfe; and, in his ſingular prudence, hath not ſo much as
taken notice, or in any of his Declarations once <hi>reproved</hi> the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable
impiety of that ſcandalous <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> for fear of further
blazing it, but rather ſuffering it to periſh in its own filthynes, and
chooſing rather to groane under the <hi>burthen</hi> of his faithfull and
abuſed Clergy, then by revengeing and painting forth the crimes
of the other party (farre more guilty) to afflict Religion
under the <hi>burthen</hi> of both.</p>
            <p>Thus is the health of our languiſhing Church <hi>impayred;</hi> thus is
the body of our craz'd Government <hi>diſtemperd;</hi> thus is the peace
of our Saviours Spouſe <hi>diſquieted;</hi> thus is the welfare of our En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
Sion <hi>determined;</hi> Her Dove-like piety is turned to <hi>Serpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi>
policy; her Unity, to <hi>Diviſion;</hi> her Uniformity, to <hi>Diſorder;</hi>
her Sanctity to <hi>Prophaneneſſe;</hi> her Needle-work robes to a <hi>parti-coloured
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:110960:13"/>
Coate;</hi> her honour into <hi>diſgrace,</hi> her glory into <hi>diſdaine,</hi>
and her proſperity into <hi>deſtruction.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 1 2.</note> She weepeth in the night,
and her teares, are in her Cheekes. Among all her <hi>Lovers</hi> there
is none to <hi>comfort</hi> her; and all her friends have delt <hi>treacherouſly</hi>
with her;<note place="margin">ver. 9.</note> Her adverſaries are the <hi>chiefe;</hi> and her <hi>enemies</hi> proſper;
for the Lord hath afflicted her for the multitude of her <hi>tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions:</hi>
Her children are gone into <hi>captivity</hi> before the Enemy,<note place="margin">2. 9.</note> and
her gates are <hi>ſunk</hi> into the Ground: Her <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> are
among the Gentiles; her <hi>law is no more,</hi> and her Prophets finde no
<hi>viſion</hi> from the Lord:<note place="margin">ver. 10.</note> The Elders of the <hi>Daughter</hi> of Sion ſit
upon the ground, and <hi>keep ſilence,</hi> and have girded themſelves
with <hi>ſackcloth;</hi> The <hi>horne</hi> of her enemies is lifted up, They ſpared
not the perſons of her <hi>Prieſts,</hi> they favoured not her <hi>Elders,</hi> they
have laid wait for the breath of our Noſtrils,<note place="margin">Lam. 4. 20.</note> 
               <hi>the Annointed of the
Lord,</hi> and ſervants beare <hi>rule</hi> over us. Our Inheritance is turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
to <hi>ſtrangers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 5. 4.</note> and our houſes to <hi>Alyants:</hi> We drink our <hi>Water</hi>
for money,<note place="margin">Lam. 3. 4.</note> and our <hi>Woods</hi> are ſold to us: We have ſinned and have
rebelled, therefore thou haſt not ſpared: For this our hearts, our
hearts faint, for theſe things our eyes are <hi>dimme;</hi> For theſe things
I weep, mine eye, mine eye <hi>runneth down</hi> with water.</p>
            <p>Where, O where are you, all you that are the wiſdom and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours
of this unhappy Iſland? Where, O where are you, the
<hi>great Counſell</hi> and grave <hi>Senators</hi> of this falling Kingdome?
Where, O where are you, the great <hi>Colledge</hi> of politicall Phyſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
of this languiſhing Common-wealth? Are ye all fallen <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep,</hi>
while we periſh? &amp; is there none to awake you? Open your
eyes, unlock your eares, and mollify your hearts: Behold, behold
the miſeries of <hi>your</hi> land, and if Compaſſion be not baniſht from
the earth, pitty, O pitty the <hi>approaching</hi> Ruines of this your
<hi>groanning,</hi> this your native kingdom. Heare O harken to the ſad
Complaints of your afflicted <hi>petitioners;</hi> and, if your hearts be
not of <hi>Adamant,</hi> relent, and let them not in vaine petition for their
<hi>lives:</hi> Let the breath of this diſtempered kingdom, contracted
into one extreame ſigh, move you to the ſpeedy endeavours of a
timely <hi>Cure.</hi> Inquire into her <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> Examine her <hi>diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,</hi>
and reduce her to her firſt <hi>Principles:</hi> Try no experiments
upon a body ſo <hi>declined,</hi> and let not the <hi>Acuteneſſe</hi> of her diſeaſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:110960:14"/>
perſwade you to a <hi>deſperate</hi> remedy, Look, O look back into the
bleſſed dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> Obſerve what bleſſings we
then had, both by Sea and Land; What <hi>plenty;</hi> what <hi>ſucceſſe;</hi>
what <hi>victories;</hi> what honour <hi>abroad;</hi> what unity at <hi>home;</hi> and
indeed what had we not that could make a kingdom happy?
Reduce us, O reduce us to that happy government; and let not
the <hi>eagerneſſe</hi> of a Reformation be a means to want men to be
<hi>Reformed,</hi> or <hi>matter</hi> for a Reformation: Remember, O remember
that great <hi>Reformer</hi> Chriſt Jeſus; He was againſt all blood ſhed,
but his <hi>own;</hi> for that <hi>blood</hi> ſake follow his Example: Or if the
way muſt needs be made by <hi>blood,</hi> let it light rather a little, upon
<hi>many</hi> Generations, then all upon <hi>one;</hi> the ruine whereof will
deny us an other <hi>Generation:</hi> Let not the children of your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſterve in <hi>the land of bread,</hi> and let not the foundations of your
naturall kingdom be longer dabled in <hi>unnaturall blood.</hi> Turne,
O turn your eyes upon her breaches, and let not ſtrangers <hi>Lord</hi> it
in her Gates. For the mercyes of that God which hath been mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
to you, be mercifull to <hi>millions</hi> of Chriſtians, whoſe lives
depend upon your <hi>Care;</hi> be mercifull to millions of <hi>children,</hi>
that know not their right hands from their left; be mercifull to
generations unborne; to whom, when deep Records ſhall bring
the <hi>Chronicles</hi> of your Actions, ages to come may magnifie your
<hi>Merits:</hi> For his ſake that is the <hi>Prince of peace,</hi> as you deſire to
meet peace upon your <hi>Death beds,</hi> let this Sea of blood already
ſpilt be thought <hi>ſufficient:</hi> For the whole body of Englands ſake,
who have <hi>truſted</hi> their power into your hands, that have caſt all
their welfares upon your wiſdomes; for their ſakes that venture
their lives and fortunes upon your providence; for your own
ſakes; for your tender wives and dear children ſakes; for the God
of <hi>mercyes</hi> ſake, as you love mercy; for Chriſt Jeſus, the God of
<hi>peace</hi> his ſake, as you prize the peace of a Good Conſcience,
hearken to, and enſue <hi>peace,</hi> while there is a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of Peace.</p>
            <p>Darken not that Religion with the <hi>black ſtorms</hi> of contenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
you profeſſe to <hi>glorifie:</hi> Leſſen not the glory of that Church,
by <hi>partiality,</hi> which you have promiſed to <hi>beautifie:</hi> Draggle
not that Goſpel in the <hi>ſinks</hi> of bloud, which you have proteſted
to <hi>magnifie:</hi> The ſinnes of <hi>Nineveh</hi> were not too great for <hi>Gods</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:110960:14"/>
compaſſion, and ſhall the offences of poore England be too great
for <hi>yours?</hi> Nineveh cryed mightily to heaven, and they were ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
and ſhall the miſeries of <hi>three Kingdomes</hi> be hollowed in
your eares, and not heard? Well, If Ruine, by a <hi>forreigne power
come,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſt. 4. 13</note> (which the God of heaven and earth forbid) think not
with your ſelves that you ſhall ſcape the <hi>Fury</hi> more then all
the reſt:<note place="margin">14.</note> But if you altogether ſtop your eares, at ſuch a time
as this, then ſhall Enlargement and Deliverance <hi>ariſe</hi> to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land
from another <hi>place,</hi> but you and your houſes ſhall be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed;
And who knowes whether you are ſent to this employment,
for ſuch a time as this?</p>
            <p>O thou that art the great preſerver of mankind, to thee, to thee
we turne the <hi>voyce</hi> of our complaint: Thou, thou art <hi>gracious,</hi>
and <hi>plentifull</hi> in Compaſſion, but in man there is no <hi>help,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 3. 24</note> nor
<hi>mercy</hi> in the ſons of men.<note place="margin">Job 13. 15.</note> Thou art my <hi>portion</hi> O God, and I
will <hi>truſt</hi> in thee,<note place="margin">Pſal. 146.</note> although thou <hi>kill</hi> me. I will not truſt in my
<hi>bow,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſ. 14. 1, 2.</note> it is not my <hi>ſhield</hi> that can ſave me, but it is <hi>thou</hi> alone, O
God, that canſt deliver us. Deliver us O God from the <hi>evil</hi> men,
preſerve us from the <hi>cruell</hi> men, which imagine evill in their
hearts, and make warre <hi>continually.</hi> Have mercy, O Lord, have
mercy upon us,<note place="margin">123. 3.</note> for we have <hi>ſuffered</hi> too much contempt. Heare
the mourning of the <hi>Priſoners,</hi>
               <note place="margin">102 20.</note> and deliver the children from
<hi>death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">83. 5.</note> They have <hi>conſulted</hi> together in heart, and have made a
<hi>league</hi> againſt thee.<note place="margin">79. 4.</note> We are a reproach to our <hi>neighbours,</hi> even a
ſcorne and deriſion to them that are <hi>round about us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">74. 10.</note> O God, how
long ſhall the Adverſary <hi>reproach</hi> thee? Shall the enemy <hi>blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme</hi>
thy Name for ever? Remember the children of <hi>Edom</hi> O
Lord in the day of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">137. 7.</note> which ſaid, <hi>Raſe it, raſe it,</hi> to the
foundations thereof.<note place="margin">132. 9.</note> Let thy Prieſts be clothed with <hi>righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
and let thy Saints <hi>rejoyce.</hi>
               <note place="margin">89. 46.</note> Lord, how long wilt thou <hi>hide
thy ſelfe?</hi> for ever? Shall thy wrath burne like fire? Wilt thou
be angry with us for ever?<note place="margin">85. 5.</note> Wilt thou <hi>prolong</hi> thy wrath from
generation to generation?<note place="margin">84. 9.</note> Behold, O God, our Shield; and look
upon the face of thine <hi>Anointed.</hi> Let thine hand be upon the <hi>man
of thy right hand,</hi> whom thou haſt made ſo <hi>ſtrong</hi> for thy ſelf. Give
thy <hi>Iudgements</hi> to the King,<note place="margin">80. 17.</note> and thy <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> to the Kings
ſonne; that peace may be in <hi>his</hi> dayes,<note place="margin">72. 1.</note> and let his <hi>enemies</hi> lick the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:110960:15"/>
duſt: Clothe his enemies with <hi>ſhame,</hi> but upon his head let his
Crowne <hi>flouriſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">132. 18.</note> How long ſhall the wicked, O Lord, how long
ſhall the wicked <hi>triumph?</hi>
               <note place="margin">94. 3.</note> They prate and ſpeak <hi>fiercely,</hi> and the
workers of iniquity <hi>vaunt</hi> themſelves. They <hi>ſmite downe</hi> thy
people, O Lord, and <hi>trouble</hi> thine Inheritance. They ſlay the
<hi>widow</hi> and the <hi>ſtranger,</hi>
               <note place="margin">115. 10.</note> and murther the <hi>fatherleſſe.</hi> O houſe of
<hi>Aaron</hi> truſt in the Lord, for he is our <hi>help</hi> and our <hi>ſhield;</hi> He will
bleſſe the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and he will bleſſe the houſe of <hi>Aaron.</hi>
Praiſe ye the Lord ye houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">135. 19.</note> praiſe ye the Lord ye houſe
of <hi>Aaron,</hi> praiſe ye the Lord ye houſe of <hi>Levi:</hi> Ye that feare the
Lord, praiſe the Lord.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 122. 6, 7, 8, 9.</bibl>
               <p>Pray for the peace of Jeruſalem: they ſhall proſper that love
thee.</p>
               <p>Peace be within thy walls, and proſperity within thy palaces.</p>
               <p>For my brethren and companions ſakes, I will now ſay, Peace
be within thee.</p>
               <p>Becauſe of the houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy good.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Hier. ſup. Epiſt. ad Rom.</bibl>
               <p>Quiſquis corpus ſuum affligit, &amp; concordiam deſerit, laudat
Deum quidem in Tympano, ſed non laudat in Chore.</p>
            </q>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:110960:15"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
